A Guide to the Virginia Press Association Archives, 1860-1988
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Virginia Press Association Archives, 1860-1988
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 269
5.7 linear feet
Virginia Press Association
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to the Special Collections and Archives Department by Thomas A. Prentice, Executive Manager of the VPA, in July of 1988.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Virginia Press Association represents virtually every newspaper in Virginia--more than 145 community weekly and daily newspapers as well as more than 100 associate and sustaining members. The association was founded in the late 19th century and was incorporated by a special act of the Virginia General Assembly in 1882. VPA has its offices in Ashland, Virginia. The business affiliate of VPA is Virginia Press Services, Inc. The VPA provides such member services as a clipping bureau, a classified ad network, awards programs, and state lobbying.
Scope and Content Information
Correspondence, minutes of the Board of Directors and various committees, reports, slides, newspaper clippings, convention information, and other papers concerning the operation of the association. Most materials date from 1935-1988; there are some materials from as early as 1860.
VPA bulletins (including the Bulletin, Confidential Bulletin, Information Bulletin, and Special Information Bulletin) have been placed in the Periodicals section under "B."
Arrangement
Arrangement
Manuscript materials are arranged alphabetically by subject in Boxes 1-3. Non-manuscript materials are arranged randomly in Boxes 4-6.
Organization
Series I--General Files (1935-1988), misc. dated earlier
Series II--Board Meeting Records
Series III--Scrapbooks
Contents List
- General Files 1935-1988
  - Advertising Award winners 1983-1986 (Box-folder 1.1)
  - Advertising Award winners 1986, 1988 (Box-folder 1.2)
  - Advertising Linage Reports 1971-1975 (Box-folder 1.3)
  - Advertising Linage Reports, 1975-1979 1975-1979 (Box-folder 1.4)
  - Advertising Linage Reports 1979-1980 (Box-folder 1.5)
  - Advertising Linage Reports 1980-1982 (Box-folder 1.6)
  - Audit--Correspondence: Smith, Robert B., Secretary-Manager VPA 1936-1938 (Box-folder 1.7)
  - Audit data, Auditor's Reports 1929-1934 (Box-folder 1.8)
  - Audit data, Auditors Reports 1937-1938, 1943 (Box-folder 1.9)
  - Better Newspaper Contest 1982-1985 (Box-folder 1.10)
  - Board of Directors 1980-1982 (Box-folder 1.11)
  - Captial City News Letters 1935-1936 (Box-folder 1.12)
  - Clippings late 1800's (Box-folder 1.13)
  - Clippings, Richardson's Almanac 1891, 1860 (Box-folder 1.14)
  - Committees 1938 (Box-folder 1.15)
  - Convention 1936 (Box-folder 1.16)
  - Convention 1936 (Box-folder 1.17)
  - Convention 1937 (Box-folder 1.18)
  - Convention 1937 (Box-folder 1.19)
  - Convention 1.20 (Box-folder 1.20)
  - Convention 1939 (Box-folder 1.21)
  - Convention 1957 (Box-folder 1.22)
  - Convention 1983, 1988 (Box-folder 1.23)
  - Convention 1988 (Box-folder 1.24)
  - Convention programs 1936-1947 (Box-folder 1.25)
  - Conventions, contests, awards, notices 19737-1939 (Box-folder 1.26)
  - Correspondence: Bottom, Major Raymond B., President VPA 1935-1936 (Box-folder 2.1)
  - Correspondence: Bottom, Major Raymond B. 1936 (Box-folder 2.2)
  - Correspondence: Bottom, Major Raymond B. 1937 (Box-folder 2.3)
  - Correspondence: Bottom, Major Raymond B. 1937-1938 (Box-folder 2.4)
  - Correspondence: miscellaneous 1936-1937 (Box-folder 2.5)
  - Correspondence: newspaper mail boxes 1936 (Box-folder 2.6)
  - Cruise 1945 (Box-folder 2.7)
  - Drunk driving campaign 1952 (Box-folder 2.8)
  - Executive Committee 1940 (Box-folder 2.9)
  - Market Data and Rate Book 1938 (Box-folder 2.10)
  - Members 1935-1936 (Box-folder 2.11)
  - Minutes 1936-1944 (Box-folder 2.12)
  - Minutes 1945-1953 (Box-folder 2.13)
  - Minutes 1953-1961 (Box-folder 2.14)
  - Minutes 1961-1969 (Box-folder 2.15)
  - Minutes 1969-1974 (Box-folder 2.16)
  - Minutes 1974-1976 (Box-folder 2.17)
  - minutes 1976-1979 (Box-folder 2.18)
  - Minutes 1979-1983 (Box-folder 2.19)
  - Miscellaneous 1936-1988 (Box-folder 2.20)
  - Newspaper interns 1981-1985 (Box-folder 2.21)
  - Newspapers, miscellaneous, n.d. 1981, 1988 (Box-folder 3.1)
  - Printed material: API, A Personal Remembrance 1980 (Box-folder 3.2)
  - Printed material: Beating the Odds(Washington Times) 1983 (Box-folder 3.3)
  - Printed material: Chauncey Durden(Richmond Times-Dispatch) 1986 (Box-folder 3.4)
  - Printed material: Excursion(Natl. Editorial Assoc.) 1891 (Box-folder 3.5)
  - Printed Material: Extra-Extra(Smithsonian Institution), n.d. (Box-folder 3.6)
  - Printed Material: Helping High School Journalists(Southern Newspaper Publisher's Assoc.) 1986 (Box-folder 3.7)
  - Printed material: miscellaneous, n.d., 1979, 1982 (Box-folder 3.8)
  - Printed material: The Sweet Season(University of Richmond) 1988 (Box-folder 3.9)
  - Printed Material: Tales of the Hill City(Lynchburg) 1986 (Box-folder 3.10)
  - Printed material: VPA advertisement 1988 (Box-folder 3.11)
  - Printed material: VPA-published 1976, 1983-1988 (Box-folder 3.12)
  - Proceedings 1912-1918 (Box-folder 3.13)
  - Proceedings, calling cards, receipts 1855, 1857, 1890-1896 (Box-folder 3.14)
  - Promotion conferences 1981-1982 (Box-folder 3.15)
  - Proof: Boston Globe 1985 (Box-folder 3.16)
  - Secretary-Manager, full time: Applications 1936 (Box-folder 3.17)
  - Secretary-Manager, full time: arguments pro and con 1935 (Box-folder 3.18)
  - Special Fund 1936 (Box-folder 3.19)
  - Telephone bills, memos 1935-1936 (Box-folder 3.20)
  - Virginia Newspaper Directories (Box-folder 3.21)
    1936, 1937, 1939-45, 1955, 1960
  - Virginia Newspaper Directories 1982-1984 (Box-folder 3.22)
  - Virginia Press, Dec-July 1985-1986 (Box-folder 3.23)
  - Print blocks (4) of VPA logo (Box 4)
  - Videocassette: VPA Creative Advertising Awards 1988 (Box 4)
  - Audio cassette: The SAU Revolution (Box 4)
  - Box of ribbons, medals, buttons, n.d. 1889-1928 (Box 4)
  - VPA stickers/labels (Box 4)
  - Slides: newspaper pages, photographs, winning entries, etc. 1976-1981-1983 (Box 5)
- Board Meeting Records
  - April Board Meeting 1987 (Box 7)
  - April Board Meeting 1987 (Box 7)
  - July Board Meeting 1987 (Box 7)
  - October Board Meeting 1987 (Box 7)
  - October Board Meeting 1987 (Box 7)
  - February Board Meeting 1988 (Box 7)
- Editorial poster(Is Dentists Bill Good Legislation?) (Oversize Drawer 25)
- The Bulletin
  1926-29 (two copies), 1929-32, 1933-37, 1943-49, 1950-52, 1956-57
- Confidential Bulletin
  July 1949-Dec. 1951, 1952-56, 1957, 1959, 1960-62, July 1963-1976
- Information Bulletin
  1936-39, July 1940-June 1945
- Publisher and Printer 1953-1972
- Special Information
  1940, 1944-46, 1956, 1958-59, July 1968-June 1970, 1971-76, plus a folder of miscellaneous issues from 1935, 1937, 1938, 1953
- Quarterly Bulletins 1919-1982
- Scrapbooks
  - Virginia Conservation Commission 1945 (Box 1)
  - The Farmville Mercury 1879 (Box 1)
  - The Press Convention Scrapbook 1874-1881 (Box 1)
  - Halifax Records 1883 (Box 1)
  - Loose Clippings (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook 1930's-1940's (Box 2)
  - Map of Virginia (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook 1938-1940s (Box 3)
  - Loose Newspaper Articles from the above scrapbook (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 1939-1942 (Box 4)
  - Loose Newspaper Articles (Box 4)
  - Roanoke 100, Centennial Edition (Box 5)
  - The Courier Journal; Highlights and Shadow; Louisville Kentucky 1930s (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings 1925-1940 (Box 5)
  - Copy of Will of Martha Washington 1788 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook 1937-1938 (Box 6)
  - Loose Clippings 1937-1938 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook 1945 (Box 6)
  - Loose Clippings 1945 (Box 6)
  - Richmond Times Dispatch, Richmond News Leader 1959-1960s (Box 7)